Louis Krasner Papers
Louis Krasner Papers
1949-1988
1971-1973
Krasner, Louis, 1903-1995.
2.25 linear ft.
Correspondence, notes, clippings, and other material relating to musician, composer, WCNY radio host, and Syracuse University music professor Louis Krasner
3546967
Biographical History
Louis Krasner (1903-1995) was a renowned Ukrainian-born American classical violinist. He is perhaps best known for commissioning and premiering Alban Berg's famous violin concerto. He studied at the New England Conservatory and performed as a virtuoso recitalist in the 1920s and 1930s. In 1944 Krasner was named concertmaster of the Minneapolis Symphony Orchestra, a post he left in1949 to join the faculty of Syracuse University where he taught violin and chamber music until 1972. He was an active contributor to local radio station WCNY, hosting a program entitled "What's With Music," and also taught at the New England Conservatory and at Tanglewood.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Louis Krasner Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, notes, clippings and other material. The majority dates from the period shortly after Krasner's retirement from Syracuse University while he was working at local radio station WCNY as host of the show "What's With Music."
Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing. Incoming includes letters to WCNY about their programming, particularly Krasner's show.
Memorabilia contains biographical material and clippings and press releases about Krasner. It also includes two photographic albums signed and inscribed by Krasner to a Mrs. Howe.
Scores contains a number of pieces of music, none written by Krasner. Composers represented include Robert Erickson, Earl George, Alexandru Hrisanide, Richard Swift and William Valente, among others.
Subject files consists of material on a variety of topics. Subjects include musicians and music in modern society; various competitions such as the Leventritt Competition and the NPR-sponsored choral competition "Let the People Sing"; proposals by Krasner shortly after his retirement; programs, clippings and Krasner's own notes for several seasons of the Syracuse Friends of Chamber Music, several of whose concerts were broadcast on WCNY; Hungarian violinist Joseph Szigreti, who died in 1973 and whose work was featured in six one-hour programs on WCNY; What's With Music, a program hosted by Krasner on WCNY; and of course several folders of material relating to WCNY and Krasner's work with them in general.
A small amount of Miscellany completes the collection. There is a set of index cards of unknown purpose (perhaps Krasner's own inventory of his papers?), and three spiral notebooks filled with Krasner's notes on music, music programs, and so on.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by type of material.
Related Material
See also the
Louis Krasner Collection of Bookplates and Ephemera
. For recordings of Krasner's performances please search or contact the repository listed above for a complete listing. The Syracuse University Archives is the repository of material related to Krasner's teaching activities in the School of Music.
Other Louis Krasner papers are held by Harvard University and the New England Conservatory.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; New York State; Eberhart, Richard, 1904-2005.; Erickson, Robert, 1917-1997.; George, Earl, 1924-1994.; Harris, Donald.; Hrisanide, Alexandru, 1936-; Krasner, Louis, 1903-1995.; Swift, Richard, 1927-2003.; Szigeti, Joseph, 1892-1973.; Valente, William, 1934-1993.; Syracuse University. -- College of Visual and Performing Arts. -- Faculty.; WCNY (Television station: Syracuse, N.Y.); American composers.; Music -- New York (State) -- Syracuse.; Music -- Instruction and study.; Radio programs.; Composers -- United States.; Violinists -- United States.; Violin teachers.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Programs (documents); Research notes.; Speeches (documents); Engravings.; Musicians.; Musicologists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Louis Krasner.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1957-1958; 1972-1973; includes letters to WCNY concerning Krasner's program (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Albums, engravings or etchings; both signed and inscribed by Krasner to a Mrs. Howe
    - Berlin, 1922 (Box 3)
    - Berlin-Potsdam, 1923 (Box 3)
  - Biographical sketches (Box 1)
  - Clippings about, 1949-1950; 1963,; 1967-1971,; 1977 (Box 1)
  - Press releases, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1948; 1973,; 1984; 2 for concerts, 1 for a conference at which Krasner participated in a panel discussion (Box 1)
- Scores
  - Manuscripts
    - Erickson, Robert: String quartet, undated; several parts, also photocopy of full score (Oversize 1)
    - Erickson, Robert: Quartet for strings, 1956 (Oversize 1)
    - George, Earl: Genevieve (…Another Fourth of July), undated; an opera in two scenes (Oversize 2)
    - Harris, Donald: Fantasy for violin and piano, 1957 (Oversize 1)
    - Hrisanide, Alexandru: Musik für mehrere violinen, undated; French, English and German (Oversize 2)
    - Hrisanide, Alexandru: Concerto per clavicembalo e orchestra, 1973; German (Oversize 2)
    - Hrisanide, Alexandru: Soliloquium x 11, 1971 (Oversize 2)
    - Huggler, John: Music in two parts for large orchestra (Op. 64), 1964-1965; "for Erich Leinsdorf and the Boston Symphony Orchestra" (Oversize 2)
    - Maneri, Joseph: Piano concerto, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Swift, Richard: Concerto for piano and chamber ensemble II, 1980 (Oversize 1)
    - Swift, Richard: Great praises for soprano and piano, 1977; poems by Richard Eberhart (Oversize 1)
    - Swift, Richard: In the country of the blue (Trio II), 1988 (Oversize 1)
    - Swift, Richard: In this corner wearing trunks, 1957-1958; poem by Helen Rowland (Oversize 1)
    - Swift, Richard: The valleys are asleep, 1972 (Oversize 1)
    - Valente, William: Shakespeare songs, 1986; includes invitation to concert and program (Oversize 1)
  - Published
    - Nowak, Lionel: Sonata for solo violin, 1952 (Oversize 1)
    - Pinkham, Daniel: Easter cantata, 1963; signed and inscribed by Pinkham to Erich Leinsdorf (Oversize 1)
    - Pinkham, Daniel: Concertante, 1963; signed and inscribed by Pinkham to Erich Leinsdorf (Oversize 1)
- Subject files
  - Let the People Sing competition, 1972-1973; NPR-sponsored choral competition (Box 1)
  - Leventritt competition, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Music Before 1600, 1972; WCNY program (Box 1)
  - Music / musicians, 1971-1973; undated; clippings relating to musicians, music education, music in general; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - New Music and the Listener, includes "statement" on new music by Krasner (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1973-1974; miscellaneous performances (Box 1)
  - Proposals, 1973; proposals by Krasner for various projects (Box 1)
  - Speculum Musicae, 1971-1973; clippings, programs, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Syracuse Friends of Chamber Music, 1971-1975; undated; programs, clippings, Krasner's notes; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Szigreti, Joseph
    - The Art of Joseph Szigreti, 1973; as presented on WCNY; clippings, notes, correspondence, etc. (Box 1)
    - Interview transcript, interviewer, date and venue unknown (Box 1)
    - Tribute to Szigeti, by Krasner, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973; clippings, copies of correspondence from Szigeti, Krasner's notes, etc. (Box 1)
  - WCNY
    - Press releases, 1973; undated (Box 2)
      See also Memorabilia: Press releases above, for WCNY press releases related to Krasner personally.
    - Publications, 1972-1975; Preview magazine (Box 2)
    - Workshop proposal, 1973; for summer workshop on media and music (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971-1973; memos, roughs of program lineups, Krasner's notes, etc. (Box 2)
  - What's With Music?, WCNY program hosted by Krasner
    - General, 1971-1974; undated; Krasner's notes for each program, sometimes biographical info about guests; Sep 1972 includes Krasner's mention of the Israeli Olympic athletes killed in Munich; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Schedules, undated (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Index cards, unknown purpose, perhaps Krasner's inventory of his papers? (Box 2)
  - Notebooks, three spiral notebooks filled with Krasner's notes; 2 folders (Box 2)